A Guide to the Virginian Railway Company records, 1906-1975
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginian Railway Company records, 1906-1975
The Library of Virginia
54301
2.3 cubic feet (7 boxes)
Virginian Railway Company
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased
Historical Information
The Virginian Railway Company was formed in 1907 with the merger of the Deepwater Railway (1898) in West Virginia with the Tidewater Railway (1904) in Virginia. The two lines were connected in 1909 and coal was shipped from the fields in West Virginia to the port of Norfolk, Virginia. The railroad benefitted from its eastern terminus being next to the United States Naval base. The Virginian Railway Company merged with Norfolk and Western in 1959.
The Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen was founded as the Conductors Union in 1868 in Illinois. The Union changed its name to the Order of Railway Conductors of America in 1878. The union became the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen in 1954. The Order merged with the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, and Switchmen's Union of North America to form the United Transportation Union in 1969.
Glenn Thomas Millican was born 21 July 1913 in Lunenburg County, Virginia, to Claude L. Millican (1889-1942) and Reva Bishop Millican (1891-1927). Millican worked as a conductor on the Virginian Railway. He married Virginia Lyle Womack (1915-1996) 5 December 1942, and they had one child. Millican died in Chesterfield County, Virginia, 26 December 1983 and was buried in the Briery Presbyterian Church Cemetery in Prince Edward County, Virginia.
Scope and Content
Records, 1906-1975, of the Virginian Railway Company consisting of freight conductor's car and tonnage record books, 1945-1975; rule books for the Virginian Railway Company, the Deepwater and Tidewater Railway Companies, and Norfolk and Western; and bulletins, correspondences, notes, timetables and other records for the Virginian Railway and for Norfolk and Western. Also includes ledger, 1951-1969, cashbook, 1956-1969, and other documents for the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
Series I: Virginian Railway Company, 1906-1956
Series II: Norfolk and Western Railway Company, 1950-1975
Series III: Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen, 1951-1972
Contents List
- Virginian Railway Company records, 1906-1956., Extent: 5 boxes. (Box 1-5)
  Virginian Railway Company records, 1906-1956, contain Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Books, 1945-1956, filled out by G. T. Millican (1913-1983), a conductor for the Virginian Railway; Safety rules and regulations and schedules for conductors, 1906-1955; timetable, 1943; and bulletins, 1953.
  - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Books, 1945-1956., Extent: 4 boxes (Box 1-4)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 19 April 1945-18 May 1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 16 August 1947-9 November 1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 29 August 1948-18 March 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 3 September-28 October 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 18 November 1951-4 January 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 5 January-17 February 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 18 February-21 March 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 22 March-19 April 1952 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 9 August-6 September 1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 8 September-11 October 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 11 October 1952-17 May 1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 22 May-9 August 1953 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 20 August 1953-28 February 1954 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 15 October 1954-31 January 1955 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 11 January-25 February 1955 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 26 February-5 April 1955 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 17 May-29 June 1955 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 30 June-1 August 1955 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 8 September-12 October 1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 13 October-12 November 1955 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 14 November 1955-11 January 1956 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, 11 January-2 February 1956 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Freight Conductor's Car and Tonnage Record Book, undated (blank) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Rules and regulations manuals and schedules for conductors, 1906-1955., Extent: 2 boxes (Box 4-5)
    - The Deepwater Railway Company and the Tidewater Railway Company, Train Rules, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - The Virginian Railway Company, Safety Rules, 1936 (two copies) (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - The Virginian Railway Company, Supplement to Rules and Regulations of the Operating Department Effective December 1, 1918 supplement effective 1 May 1942 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - The Virginian Railway Company, Rules of the Operating Department, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - The Virginian Railway Company, Safety Rules, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - The Virginian Railway Company, Rules of Equipment Operation and Handling for the Government of Train and Engine Service Employees of the Operating Department, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - The Virginian Railway Company, Schedule for Conductors, 1946 (copy one) (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - The Virginian Railway Company, Schedule for Conductors, 1946 (copy two) (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - The Virginian Railway Company, Rules of Equipment Operation and Handling for the Government of Train and Engine Service Employees of the Operating Department, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - General papers, 1943, 1953., Extent: 1 box (Box 5)
    - The Virginian Railway Company, Time Table No. 19 effective 8 August 1943 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - The Virginian Railway Company, Bulletin 4: Seniority Roster of Road Conductors and Bulletin 5: Seniority Roster of Road Brakemen, 1 January 1953 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Norfolk and Western Railway Company records, 1950-1975., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 5, 7)
  Norfolk and Western Railway Company records, 1950-1975, contain notices, 1950-1961; rules and regulations, 1951; rates of pay, 1967; pamphlets, 1968; train book, 1975; correspondence and general papers, 1960-1968; blank form books; and photograph.
  - Notices, 1950-1961 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Norfolk and Western Railway Company, Rules and Regulations for the Government of the Operating Department, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and general paeprs, 1960-1968 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Road Conductors: Current Rates of Pay effective 1 August 1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Association of American Railroads, Bureau of Explosives, Pamphlet No. 6C: Illustrating Methods for Loading and Bracing Trailers and Less-Than Trailer Shipments of Explosives and Other Dangerous Articles Via Trailer-on-Flat-Car (TOFC) or Container-on-Flat-Car (COFC), September 1968 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Norfolk and Western Railway Company Conductor's Train Book, 27 September-26 November 1975 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Norfolk and Western Railway Company Form C. T. 34--work log(?), no date (blank--copy one of two) (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Norfolk and Western Railway Company Form C. T. 34--work log(?), no date (blank--copy one of two) (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Norfolk and Western Railway Company--photograph of steam engines (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Order of Railroad Conductors and Brakemen records, 1951-1972., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 6-7)
  Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen records, 1951-1972, contain correspondence, 1956-1961; Labor Relations Institute, University of Louisville, program, 1968; United Transportation Union time books, 1970-1972; membership ledger, 1951-1969; and cash book, 1956-1969.
  - Correspondence, 1956-1961 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - University of Louisville, Learning While Earning, Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen: Know Your Order and How It Works, Labor Relations Institute, 25-26 May 1956 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - United Transportation Union Time Book, 1970-1971 (blank) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - United Transporation Union Time Book, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen ledger, 1951-1969 (Box 7)
  - Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen cash book, 1956-1969 (Box 7)